[Music]
sometimes there's a glitch in the matrix
where the limitations of the old
operating system are laid bare and
something new pokes through there's been
dozens of responses to the jordan
peterson channel for interview already
what makes this one different well I
have a pretty unique perspective in
October last year I went to Toronto to
interview Jordan Peterson at his home
you came in from where I came in from
London
last night I turned the interview into
the first full-length documentary about
Jordan Peterson's ideas I was pretty
sure he'd soon become a lot more famous
and be recognized as one of the most
significant public thinkers but I
couldn't possibly have predicted how
he'd break through to a mass audience a
few weeks later Peterson did an
interview with journalist Kathy Newman
on channel 4 news in the UK a program I
worked on as a reporter and producer for
ten years it was a sensation millions
watched it online
tens of thousands commented an
overwhelming majority felt Peterson had
been unfairly represented
[Music]
and in the week since it hasn't stopped
Peterson has been asked about it
constantly on the most high-profile
online shows 12 rules for life so
without reading this so what you're
saying is there's only 12 things you
need to do in life right that's it
well yeah this this interview that you
just did with this woman Kathy Newman
shit was that in the UK it was Channel 4
UK so what does this glitch say about
the state of mainstream media and the
culture at large by diagnosis of what's
actually happening is that people are
moving further and further away from
what is what thinking actually is I'm at
or more into merely running a script and
what does Jordan Peterson actually think
that's so controversial you are
misrepresented more than anyone I know
in a weird way you are villainized in a
weird way where I can't believe that
these people are honestly looking at
your opinions and coming up with these
conclusions
I believe this encounter struck such a
nerve because it's a cultural watershed
moment it seemed properly as Peterson
would say it's archetypal in that it
contains layers and layers of meaning to
go right to the heart of the biggest
rift we're seeing playing out in the
culture over the next 50 minutes I'm
gonna do my best to unpack it from the
clash between new and old media there's
also why YouTube is gonna kill TV
because television by its nature all of
these narrow broadcast technologies they
rely on forcing the story all the way
down to the mythological an archetypal
level I thought of ideologies as
fragmentary mythologies that's where
they get their archetypal and
psychological power but in the
postmodern world and this seems to be
something that's increasingly seeping
out into the culture at large you have
nothing but the tyrannical father
nothing but the destructive force of
masculine consciousness and nothing but
the banal
benevolent great mother and it's a it's
an appalling ideology and it seems to me
that it's sucking the vitality which is
exactly what you would expect
symbolically it's sucking the vitality
of her culture and to ask how do we move
forward constructively rather than just
adding to the polarization I've been a
journalist for 16 years in the newsrooms
of the BBC in channel 4 and then making
documentaries I moved away from the
frontline of news some time ago and
started learning psychology which is
what first drew me to Jordan Peterson
from a distance I've started to see the
blind spots of the establishment media
much more clearly
I spent some of the best years of my
working life at Channel 4 News and have
a huge amount of respect and gratitude
to the program but I'm making this film
because I feel so strongly that if we
can't have open conversations about the
kind of topics Peterson is raising we're
in serious trouble my book went up to
number two and on amazon.com in the US
the next day right it's number one in
Canada it's number three in the UK all
on Amazon I couldn't have asked for more
publicity right and so I could also be
sitting back and saying well you know
she tried to my a person who regarded
herself as my ideological opponent tried
to go after my philosophy and my
reputation on national TV failed
brutally and has been taken apart for it
it's like this is a good day but I don't
regard it as a good day I don't think
it's a good day I think that it's
evidence of the instability of the times
that we're in it would have been much
better for me and for everyone else if
what we would have had was a real
conversation you said that it's actually
a sign of the times where things could
go really wrong for all of us really
soon yeah we're playing with fire yeah
what do you mean by this can you can you
elaborate
well things go wrong in cultures all the
time right you get you get the
polarization increases until people
start to act it out
Peterson is one of a new breed of
thinkers made famous almost completely
by the internet not the broadcast media
part of a powerful new informal network
being called the intellectual dark web
the mainstream media is based on an old
dying model that is being replaced by
new media and new technology so quickly
that its faults are becoming glaringly
obvious fortunately thanks to YouTube
podcasting and however else you get
shows like this one the mainstream
media's stranglehold on information
which really is a stranglehold on your
ability to think clearly about the
issues of the day is crumbling at an
incredible rate now the question is who
and what will replace it a few months
ago one of my favorite people to sit
across this table from Eric Weinstein
came up with the phrase intellectual
dark web to describe this eclectic mix
of people from Sam Harris to Ben Shapiro
to his brother Brett Weinstein to jordan
peterson all of whom are figuring out
ways to have the important and often
dangerous conversations that are
completely ignored by the mainstream
it's why i would argue that this
collection of people are actually more
influential at this point than whatever
collection of cable news pundits you can
come up with if you think I'm being
hyperbolic about the growing influence
of this group just check the traction
that these people get on Twitter or
Facebook compared to our mainstream
competitors twitter may not be real life
as I say in my Twitter bio but it is
some barometer of what the zeitgeist is
right now what unites this group of
thinkers is a sense that the set of
ideas that have run Western culture for
years are breaking down and that the
chaos of the moment is the attempt to
find new ones it's nearly all happening
online part of the problem that we have
right now in our culture is trying to
diagnose the level at which the
discussion should be taking place and I
think the reason that this is a
tumultuous time is because it actually
is a time for discussion of first
principles and it's it's that first
principles are virtually at the level of
theology because first principles are
the things that you assume and then move
forwards like well what should we assume
well the dignity of the human soul let's
start with that you can't treat yourself
properly without assuming that you
can have a relationship with another
person you can't stabilize your family
you can't have a functional Society
so what does it mean for this human soul
to have dignity well the part of the
idea is that you're participating in
creation itself and you do that with
your actions in your language and you
get to decide whether you're tilting the
world a bit more towards heaven or a bit
more towards hell and that's actually
what you're doing so that's a place
where the literal and the metaphorical
truth comes together and people are very
they're terrified of that idea as they
should be because it's a massive
responsibility they also argue that the
central problem is polarization boosted
by social media
Peterson's work looks at how people are
hard-wired to see the world differently
a lot of what determines your political
orientation is biological temperament
far more than people realize so for
example left-leaning people liberals
let's say although that's kind of MIS
misnomer but we'll keep with the
terminology liberals are high in a trait
called openness which is one of the big
five personality traits and it's
associated with interest in abstraction
and interest in aesthetics it's the best
predictor of liberal political leaning
and they're low in trait
conscientiousness which is dutifulness
and and orderliness in particular
whereas the Conservatives are the
opposite they're high in
conscientiousness they're dutiful and
orderly and they're low in openness and
that makes them really good managers and
administers ministers and often
businessman but not very good
entrepreneurs because the entrepreneurs
are almost all drawn from the liberal
types and so these are really
fundamental fundamentally biologically
predicated differences and they're you
might think about them as different sets
of opportunities and limitations and and
certainly different ways of screening
the world and each of those different
temperamental types needs the other type
let's call this a diversity issue if you
start understanding that the person that
you're talking to who doesn't share your
political views isn't stupid that's the
first thing necessarily they might be
but so might you be no stupid
he isn't the differences in intelligence
are not the prime determinant of
differences in political belief all
right so you might be talking to someone
who's more conscientious and less
creative than you if you're if you
happen to be a liberal but that doesn't
mean that that person's perspective is
not valid and it doesn't mean that they
wouldn't outperform you in some domains
because they would so one thing to
remember is people actually do see the
world differently it's not merely that
they that they're possessed of illy
informed opinions the whole point of the
de democracy is to continue the dialogue
between people of different
temperamental types so that we don't
move so far to the right that everything
becomes encapsulated and stoned and
doesn't move or so far to the left that
everything dissolves in a kind of
mealy-mouthed chaos and the only way
that you can you can navigate between
those two shoals is by is through
discussion which is why free speech is
such an important value it's the thing
that keeps the temperamental types from
being at each other's throats in the
aftermath of the Trump election that
came as such a shock to most of the
media one of the most widely shared
analysis pieces was from deep code it
describes how the establishment
mainstream media perspective based
around liberal values of openness and
inclusivity he calls the blue church is
being challenged by a new web-based
insurgency a red religion based on the
values of tribalism the culture were the
the 20th century was a decisive success
for blue and a effectively a route for
red so what we see first is that red was
forced to move into a deeply exploratory
phase second that it did this in a
context where as it turns out things
were changing meaningfully quite
significantly in fact it from my
perspective in a world historical level
the emergence of entirely new forms of
communication and therefore entirely new
form
sense-making incoherent he concludes
that the blue church is in the process
of collapse as its dominant ideology
can't adapt to changing reality but that
a combination of the two sets of values
of blue and red is essential we are
conscious and effective in the world in
groups not as individuals and the
ingredients of those groups include
aspects that are currently showing up as
both red and blue I propose somewhat
strongly that neither red nor blue as
pure elements contain the ingredients
necessary to actually be adaptive to
reality this is a disaster in fact it's
a little bit like separating the hand
and the eye yeah you're the eye can see
if the eye takes itself as being the
essence of virtue it separates itself
from the ability to do the same thing
with the hand for most of human history
these groups have actually always
commingled they're necessary that they
actually relate to each other in a
deeply healthy and direct fashion their
separations and two armed camps is
extinction area actually you know the
values of red that you think blue needs
to integrate or to make or to
reintegrate oh oh that's actually pretty
easy responsibility I mean we've
actually even seen it the ability to
make a commitment and keep it which
which by the way ideologically shows up
is either duty or loyalty but those are
both ideologies the the deeper sense is
that ability responsibilities both of
the individual in the group level the
ability to actually really make a
personal sacrifice on the part of the
group that's actually a deeply read
while you and I don't mean that by the
way as politically ideological certainly
there are people who are currently part
of blue who feel that deeply what I'm
saying is that that that shows up much
much more intensely in
read and when you're feeling it in blue
you're actually feeling a red value and
that's good mixing that's crucial
because that's very jordan peterson
esque - how would you how do you define
jordan peterson or do you think the fact
the issue is that he is is not definable
within one of those two camps yeah I
think that's the point I think that he
grasps directly the fact that human
beings can only actually make sense of
the world by virtue of communication
with other human beings and this is all
about the notion of admixture that one
must have a mixture of of whoa I mean he
uses the mythopoetic to make sense they
order order and chaos the way right the
Daoist way is the alchemical admixture
of order and chaos and that's it like
that's how you do it and so if you bias
towards orderliness you find yourself in
a rigid non adaptive non creative non
exploratory framework which will die
because the world changes
if you bias towards chaos you you eat
your young and evaporate which also ties
for obvious reasons and the key is to
actually enable these things to be in
relationship with each other and vital
healthy relationship with each other and
I think that's in some sense the essence
of what he's focusing on and instead of
the core what he's acting about Peterson
is hard for the broadcast media to get a
handle on because the depth of his
thought means he doesn't fit easily into
any of their categories the clash with
Kathy Newman was his breakthrough moment
where the new world met the old to give
the context from Kathy Newman side she
has to do dozens of interviews each
month Peterson is hard to get a grip on
and he sure as hell looks controversial
she's also focused on getting sound
bites for a five minute cut down of the
interview for TV not a long conversation
for online the interview was ridiculous
it was a ridiculous interview I listen
to it or watched it several times I was
like this is so strange
it's like her determination to turn into
a conflict - it's one of the issues that
I have with television shows yeah
because they have a very limited amount
of time and they're trying to make
things
hellacious as possible they won't have
these soundbites this clickbait
soundbites and she just went into it
incredibly confrontational not trying to
find your actual perspective but trying
to force you to defend a non non
realistic perspective yes well I was
that I was the hypothetical villain of
her imagination essentially no this is
also why YouTube is gonna kill TV
because television by its nature all of
these narrow broadcast technologies they
rely on forcing the story right because
it has to happen now it has to happen in
like often in five minutes because they
only broadcast five minutes of that
interview they did put the whole thing
up on YouTube to their credit it it it
hasn't ceased to amaze me yet I think
that they thought that the interview
went fine after the interview Channel
four News found themselves at the center
of an online storm which included some
nasty personal and misogynistic attacks
it's understandable that they just
wanted it to go away
but online is forever and as the center
of gravity continues to shift away from
traditional media this interview is I
would argue a slow-motion and continuing
car crash for Channel 4's credibility so
why did it happen partly the limitations
of the medium of TV but also because of
the institutional political blindness of
the mainstream media I've always
considered myself of the liberal left
but especially since the election of
Trump I've been trying to understand
what happened and I'm convinced that the
polarization we're seeing is mainly
driven by the shadow side of liberalism
in particular where supposedly inclusive
social justice liberalism stops being
inclusive and secretly judges and
despises people that don't think the
same way the rebellion of Trump and
brexit was a direct response as Yuri
Harris argues in this article in Colet
the new gatekeepers of the media have
become a new bourgeoisie enforcing a
rigid etiquette and using the rights of
the oppressed as an excuse to put
forward a vision of the kind of society
they personally want to live in on the
surface level it's about how a narrow
social justice worldview embodied by
Kathy Newman in the interview became the
new status quo and how this
institutional bias of much of the
mainstream media means it can't see or
understand the forces that are
challenging this new consensus the
counterculture used to be on the left
but once it won the culture war it left
space for a new counterculture the
biggest manifestation is the red pill
phenomena which the mainstream media
mistakenly assumes is the same thing as
the alt-right I was surprised to just
discover the overlap between what I'm in
as he particularly liked Greek
philosophy and stoicism and the
alt-right
who I had always thought of you know if
I come across in the tour
the most kind of swivel-eyed bogeymen
you know completely unpalatable
extremists in their in their basements
and then to discover that you know a lot
of them were a lot of people into
stoicism were also really into the old
Reich made me wonder what was going on
and why people like me we're getting
radicalized and drawn in to explain what
stoicism is for stoicism is basically an
ancient Greek philosophy which was
became very popular in the Roman Empire
you know with like the Emperor Marcus
Aurelius was a stoic for example and
it's in some ways like a Western form of
Buddhism it's like a therapy for the
emotions it teaches you to take
responsibility for your thoughts to take
and thereby to take some control over
your emotions so in some ways it's
putting forward a model of strength and
integrity and kind of resilience amid
adversity and rapid change so for that
reason it's become very popular in the
last ten years I think this is also why
from my perspective at least someone
like Jordan Pederson is often looked
from the outside as being aligned with
the alt-right because he has a similar
message but it's but there are crucial
differences I think between what we
would consider I mean certainly white
nationalism would be an essential part
of the art right I would say of any
useful definition and yeah that's that's
certainly not characteristic of of
Jordan Peterson from my experience no
there's a crucial difference at least
between stoicism and the art right even
though a lot of alt writers and
histories and in that stoicism and and
maybe Jordan Peterson as well I don't
know I'm not an expert on him talk about
the way to gain strength and maturity
and power is internal it's to take
responsibility for your own thoughts and
feelings whilst I think people sometimes
men might look for that sense of power
control externally by suppressing or
segregating anyone who they feel
threatened by whether that's other
colors or other sexualities or gender so
there's a crucial difference there one
is about kind of inner integrity and and
and just kind of being strong within
yourself and the other is about trying
to take control through the kind of
exterior orders every public appearance
that I've made that's related to the
sort of topics that we're discussing his
overwhelmingly men it's like it's like
eighty-five to ninety percent and so I
thought wow that's weird like what the
hell's going on here exactly and then
the other thing I've noticed is that
I've been talking a lot to the crowds
that I've been talking to not about
rights but about responsibility right
because he can't have the bloody
converse what are you doing you can't
have the conversation about rights
without the conversation about
responsibility because your rights are
my responsibility that's what they are
technically so you just can't have only
half of that discussion and we're only
having half that discussion and the
question is well what the hell are you
leaving out if you only have that half
of the discussion and the answer is what
you're leaving out responsibility and
then the question is well what are you
leaving out if you're leaving out
responsibility and the answer might be
well maybe you're leaving out the
meaning of life that's what it looks
like to me it's like here you are
suffering away what makes it worthwhile
right you know you're completely oh
you're completely you have no idea what
you're you it's almost impossible to
describe how bad an idea that is
responsibility that's what gives life
meaning
it's like lift a load then you can
tolerate yourself right because look at
your useless easily hurt easily killed
why should you have any self-respect
that's the story of the fall pick
something up and carry it pick make it
heavy enough so that you can think yeah
well useless as I am at least I could
move that from there to there well
what's really cool about that is that
when I talk to these crowds about this
the man's
eyes light up and that's very like I've
seen that phenomena because I've been
talking about this mythological material
for a long time and I can see when I'm
watching crowds people you know their
eyebrows lift their eyes let light up
because I put something together for
them
that's what mythological stories do so
I'm not taking responsibility for that
that's what the stories do so I save the
story people go click click click you
know in their eyes light up
but this responsibility thing that's a
whole new order of this is that young
men are so hungry for that it is
unbelievable it just blows me away it's
like really that's what's that's the
counterculture grow the hell up and do
something useful really I could do that
oh I'm so excited by that idea no one
ever mentioned that before
it's like rights rights rights rights
Jesus it's it's it's appalling it's it's
and and I feel that that's deeply felt
by the people who are who are coming out
to to listen to these sorts of things to
they're they've had enough of that so
and they better have because it's it's a
non-productive mode of being
responsibility man Peterson is part of
the counterculture that he describes
himself as a classic liberal and yet
he's frequently described as right-wing
by the media this is not limited to
Peterson James d'amours
infamous Google memo was described
everywhere as an anti diversity screed
despite him specifically stating he
wanted to encourage more diversity in
the workplace many believe that the
Channel 4 interview was a significant
moment in exposing this mindset as
dogmatic reactionary and fixed so during
the interview we see an example of a
delusional framework that is what
appears to be largely incapable of
perceiving and reacting to reality in
real time but much more interesting is
what happened afterwards which was the
sort of the self-healing and policing
mechanism of the larger social consensus
of how when have a blue church
reactively goes about maintaining the
integrity
it's frame and so what ended up happened
was there was a break in the frame there
was a glitch in the matrix the
mechanisms of the blue church reacted to
endeavor to control the frame and to
convert it into a way of sense of making
sense of the what occurred that still
maintained the integrity of its frame do
you mean when they tried to characterize
it as sort of abusive trolls and you're
right hero and all of that exactly
exactly the sort of a to use of a
military language it was a fallback
position that was a reactive almost
instinctual and not almost in fact
precisely instinct was that pure habit
there was no thoughtfulness or even
strategic action there it was if if X
then Y and in this case y is here's a
set of things that one does to
re-establish the dominant frame and now
we're now were two levels deep in the
first level was a sort of self-evident
disaster but then the second level was
also a relatively self-evident disaster
and there isn't really a third level in
this approach so it ends up happening
and this is again you can kind of just
think about this from ordinary
psychology this is how delusions fall
apart as try as we might our desire to
interpret reality to mean what we wanted
to mean at the end of the day we'll
always be checked against what reality
actually is it may be some time you know
we're pretty good at making things up
and pretending but eventually reality is
reality this isn't to say that Peterson
is not controversial he's saying things
that challenge the most deeply held
assumptions of the new establishment
narrative I guess the other reason that
people are on my case to some degree is
because I have made a strong case which
I think is fully documented by the
scientific literature that there are
intrinsic differences say between men
and women and I think the evidence and
that this is the thing that staggered me
is that no serious scientists have
debated that for like four decades
it's that argument was done by the time
I went to graduate school
everyone knew that human beings were not
a blank slate that biological forces not
parameterised the way that we thought
and and felt and acted and and and
valued everyone knew that the fact that
this has become somehow debatable again
is just especially because it's being
done by legislative Fiat they're forcing
it part of Peterson's argument based on
years of psychological research is that
much of the political conflicts are due
to try to integrate the different
political temperaments of men and women
we were talking about the relatively the
relative evolutionary roles of men and
women this is speculative obviously and
and because our research did indicate
it's tentative research so far that that
the the the SGS SJW sort of equality
above all else philosophy is more
prevalent among women it's predicted by
the personality factors that are more
common among women so agreeable this and
high negative emotion primarily
agreeableness but in addition it's also
predicted by being female and so I've
been thinking about that a lot because
well men are bailing out of the
humanities like mad and pretty much out
of the universities except for stem the
women are moving in like mad and they're
also moving into the political sphere
like mad and this is new right we've
never had this happen before and we do
know no do not know what the
significance of it is it's only fifty
years old and so we were thinking about
this and so I don't know what you think
about this proposition but imagine that
that that historically speaking it's
something like women were responsible
for distribution and men were
responsible for production something
like that and maybe maybe that's only
the case really in the tight confines of
the immediate family but that doesn't
matter because that's most of the
evolutionary landscape for human beings
anyways what the women doesn't did was
make sure that everybody got enough okay
and that seems to me to be one of the
things that's driving at least in part
the SJW demand for for equity and
equality it's like let's make sure
everybody has enough it's like look fair
enough you know I mean you can't you
can't argue with that but there's
there's an antipathy
between that and the the reality of
differential productivity you know
because people really do differ in their
productivity I think that the SJW
phenomena is different and I think it is
associated at least in part with the
rise of women to political power and and
we don't know what women are like when
they have political power because
they've never had it I mean there's been
Queens obviously and that sort of thing
there's been female authority figures
and females have wielded far more power
historically than feminists generally
like to admit but this is a different
thing and we don't know what what a
truly female political philosophy would
be like but it might be especially if
it's not been well examined and it isn't
very sophisticated conceptually it could
easily be let's make sure things are
distributed equally well yeah sorry why
[Music]
one of Peterson's main influences is the
psychologist Carl Jung young psychology
was built around the concept of the
shadow all the things about ourselves we
don't want to accept our anger
negativity unconscious judgments and how
we need to integrate all those disowned
parts to grow I'm convinced that's
what's happening on a vast cultural
level since leaving channel 4 news
I've retrained as a counselor and
started leading personal growth
workshops for men and thought a lot
about how these unconscious gender
dynamics are playing out in the culture
one of the central concepts is Jung's
idea of animus and anima possession how
we each have both an inner masculine and
feminine essence in a man when he's
unconsciously possessed by his feminine
side his anima he becomes withdrawn
Moody and reactive and when a woman is
possessed by her male side the animus
she becomes aggressive and dominating
and how many women are pushed into that
by the nature of the modern workplace
the Kathy Newman I know is warm
compassionate a successful and talented
journalist none of this is criticism of
her just the role she was playing in the
into
I would say technically and this is
might be interesting for people who are
interested in Union psychology if you
want to understand what Carl Jung meant
by animus possession which is a very
difficult concept then that that
interview was a textbook case of having
a discussion with someone who is animus
possessed life has been moving forward
for three and a half billion years and
it moves forward in these pattern
manners like the dominance hierarchy for
example so that's that let's call that
the masculine archetype it's part of the
masculine archetype in fact the onus
Proclamation was that the female
representation of the male so that's the
animus is the dominance hierarchy it's
the patriarchy so that's that that's the
unconscious archetype which i think is
extremely interesting given what's
happened say in the women's movement
because that's what's projected on to
man and and it can be projected in a
very negative way it doesn't have to be
but it can be and so an animus possessed
woman treats a man as if he's the
manifestation of the tyrannical
patriarchy
he's a group he's that group of men yeah
the group of bad man naturally you watch
the Jordan Peterson Kathy Nieman
interview what did he what did he think
oh I my whole body contracted and I I
felt so sad for womanhood I felt
disappointed and I could see how the
shadow part of womanhood was acting out
I could see how the collective rage was
acting through Kathy Newman and this is
what happens is that when that's unknown
its projected blindly on to whatever
stick wherever it sticks and it was very
clear that she already had an agenda and
she already had a projection that she
was just looking to state she was she
was just looking to have that confirmed
so I felt on behalf of women I felt sad
and disappointed because we need
to have intelligent conversations and I
also want to say that this isn't even
though that the specific example is the
Kathy Newman Jordan Peters an interview
it's not specific to to Kathy Newman I
think the fact that that interview has
resonated with so many people that it's
been so popular shows that actually
something archetypal was going on in
that in that interaction and I think as
well why it's gone viral is a lot of
people watching it recognize those
dynamics they're like I've been in
conversations like that I've been in
this conversation where nothing I say
works but nothing I say gets through so
there's something sort of fundamental
about about the masculine feminine
dynamic that's going on in there
what do you think that is I think Jordan
Peterson he's everyman Kathy Newman
she's every woman I can tap into that
rage like this I know it in myself and
women that say they don't they're just
denying it because it is in the
collective so in that sense it just
highlighted what what's that it's
wonderful because here we really get to
look at why is this so important why is
it so important to listen to to a
thinker like Jordan Peterson and take it
seriously and say what can we do with it
it's just so obvious that it's needed
because if this is where we are if this
is where society and cultures is if this
is the ability to have an intelligent
conversations conversation then we are
in trouble I really feel that there is
this collective subconscious rage that
is just boiling in women and it's coming
up in so many ways we see we see in the
media and what's going on is this
unknown rage that comes up in in many
different ways and on one hand it needs
to come out we need to clear it it needs
to be expressed it needs to be
acknowledged on the other hand it's not
enough this is only like this is
breaking the ice so that the next step
of evolution can
you know consciousness can start coming
through and that's what I'm lacking in
women it's really to take responsibility
for what we do as women in our
manipulation in our seduction in our
control and and it's so easy for women
to say but that's just because we're
angry and men did this and patriarchy
but it's it's such a lack of
responsibility and this women really
need to know I mean that's the the kind
of shadow work is the acceptance that we
all have shadows that men certainly have
a shadow there is a shadow around
masculinity but there's also a shadow
around femininity and while part of the
cultural conversation now is toxic
masculinity and everyone knows what you
mean by toxic toxic masculinity if you
talk about toxic femininity everyone
still knows what you mean but you can't
have that conversation which is it's
it's interesting what is allowed to be
said and what is not allowed to be said
at the moment and that dad I think is is
very dangerous that certain topics
certain conversations are off are
off-limits and this is where we see
where we see the victim persecutor
dynamics activates it because women
become the become the victims and we
make ourselves the victims and we
persecute men but in that aggression in
that reach and when we are the victims
we are in perfect control we become the
persecutors because we say it's all
about blame men did this and men need to
take responsibility but in that we
become the persecutors and it's also
very difficult as well because one
imagines that that combative attitude is
something that has served her well in
the past and it's something that she's
maybe felt forced into because of the
nature of the society that she's
operating in so it's a kind of catch-22
situation for the many successful women
because they feel that they're pushed to
be more masculine and then when they're
more masculine they get judged for being
more masculine it's it's very sad
and and and I can see that dynamics
being played out absolutely but I think
the only thing we can do is to take
responsibility and say okay I'm doing
that do I really want to compromise my
femininity do I want to compromise my
integrity
do I want to compromise my gender and
play that or is there another way that I
can be powerful without being aggressive
without playing a power game but resting
in my natural power resting in my
natural dignity resting in that deep
rootedness that we both have in our
genders that when we are peace with it
and when we acknowledge it in ourselves
it's there as a natural thing and and
this is the thing I don't want to make
this personal about Kathy Newman because
it's it's in that potential is in every
woman but it's because we are
persecuting our own femininity what's
being played out that we're doing it to
ourselves because we don't trust that
it's good enough to be a woman we don't
trust that we can have conversations
that come from a felt embodied
perspective we don't trust that we're
connected to truth because these these
masculine ways have been have been very
strong and women have been denying their
own power in my work over many years of
working with this I find that very few
women grew up in households which really
loved admired respected honored
cherished the feminine and so there is
intrinsically for so many women who've
grown up in the I don't know the last
hundred years that say a kind of
devaluation of the feminine that gets
taken on and of course and as well as
abuse aggression all sorts of things so
very many women out of an intelligent
strategy to survive develop their
masculine side as a defense against that
devaluation for the feminine and over
time they become very identified with
that masculine side the male equivalent
is animal possession in anima possession
it's the loss of relaxed confidence in
the groundedness in
: and is overwhelmed by his own inner
feminine side and it creates a a passive
withdrawn moody bitchy complaining not
showing up kind of guy which i think is
really so much what feminists are angry
about I don't see them as really angry
about the masculine per se but it the
way that males behave and you know I
have got a lot of compassion for that
because for myself and most men that I
know we weren't really shown how to be
as men we didn't really get initiated
into it and so and then this strong
thing comes from feminism and we feel
like it's it's maleness that's wrong and
it's not it's not maleness that's wrong
I don't even think feminism feminists
hate the masculine it's like what the
call is really for men is to develop
their masculine strength presence
courage be relaxed and confident be
protective and be strong and under this
kind of assault which has come from a
lot of animus possessed women a lot of
men have retreated and I think gone into
feeling guilty about being men and have
become passive indecisive and in that
way a kind of feminized man has emerged
[Music]
those who followed Peterson's thought
recognize his analysis goes all the way
down to the bedrock to the archetypal
structures of consciousness itself the
thing that I really see happening and
you can tell me what you think about
this in annoyance book consciousness
which is masculine symbolically
masculine for a variety of reasons is is
viewed as rising up against the
countervailing force of tragedy from an
underlying feminine symbolically
feminine unconsciousness right and it's
something that can always be pulled back
into that unconsciousness that would be
the microcosm of that would be the
Freudian eatable mother family dynamic
where the mother was so over protective
and all-encompassing that she interferes
with the development of the competence
not only of her son's but also of her
daughter's of her children in general
and it seems to me that that's the
dynamic that's being played out in our
society right now is that there's this
and it's it's related in some way that I
don't understand to this to this
insistence that all forms of masculine
Authority are nothing but tyrannical
power so the symbolic representation is
tyrannical father with no appreciation
for the benevolent father and benevolent
mother with no appreciation whatsoever
for the tyrannical mother right and
that's that and because I thought of
ideologies as fragmentary mythologies
that's where they get their archetypal
and psychological power right and so in
a balanced representation you have the
terrible mother and the great mother as
Norman played out so nicely and you have
the terrible father and the great father
so that's the fact that culture mangles
you have to death well it's also
promoting you in developing you you have
to see that as balanced and then you
have the heroic and adversarial
individual but in the postmodern world
and this seems to be something that's
increasingly seeping out into the
culture at large you have nothing but
the tyrannical father nothing but the
destructive force of masculine
consciousness and nothing but the
benevolent benevolent great mother and
it's a it's an appalling ideology and it
seems to me that it's sucking the
vitality which is exactly what you would
expect symbolically it's sucking the
vitality of our culture you see that
with the increasing demolition of young
men and not only young men in terms of
their academic performance which like
they're falling way behind in elementary
school way behind in junior high and
bailing out of the universities like mad
and so and I well the public school
education is become completely permeated
by this kind of my anti male propaganda
I mean and I need to me public schools
are just a form of imprisonment you know
right now they're particularly
destructive to young men who have a lot
of physical energy you know you know I
identify as transgender getting myself
way but I do not I do not require the
entire world to alter itself okay to fit
my particular in the self-image I do
believe in the power of hormones I
believe that men exist and women exist
and they are biologically different I
think that I think there is no cure for
the cultures ills right now except if
men start standing opera in demanding
that they be respected as men here's the
problem you know this is something my
wife is pointed out to she said well men
are gonna have to stand up for
themselves but here's the problem I know
how to stand up to a man who's who's
unfairly trespassing against me and the
reason I know that is because the
parameters for my resistance are quite
well defined which is we talk we argue
we push and then it becomes physical
right like if we move beyond the
boundaries of civil discourse we know
what the next step is ok that's
forbidden in in discourse with women so
I don't know like it seems to me that it
isn't men that have to stand up and say
enough of this even though that is what
they should do it seems to me that it's
same women who have to stand up against
their crazy sisters and say look enough
of that enough man-hating enough
pathology enough bringing disgrace on us
as a gender but the problem there and
then I'll stop my little tirade is that
most of the women I know who are saying
are busy doing same things right they're
off they have their career they have
their family they're quite occupied and
they don't seem to have the time or
maybe even the interest to go after
their their crazy harpy sisters and so I
don't see any regulating force for that
that terrible femininity and it seems to
me to be invading the culture and
undermining the the masculine power of
the culture in a way that's I think
fatal I really do believe that I too I
too believe these are symptomatic of the
decline of Western culture and we and it
will just go down flat I don't think
people realize that you know masculinity
still exists okay in the world as a code
among jihadists okay and when you have
passionate masculinity okay
circling the borders like the Huns and
the Vandals during the
empire that's what I see I see this
culture rotting from within okay and and
disembowelling itself literally we have
this bit of combat let's say it produced
a scandal now we actually talk about it
yeah
no tricks just a conversation and then
everybody wins right because I can admit
whatever mistakes I made she can admit
whatever mistakes she made we can drop
the persona so you're saying the
polarization that we're seeing right now
that we are speaking out it's not in the
future we will act out that polarization
if we don't if we keep accelerating it
especially if we keep accelerating with
lies yeah you know and and this this
whole channel for rat's nest is like 90%
lies maybe more and you know a lot of
its ideologically motivated lies but it
doesn't matter it still lies like Kathy
as I said there was virtually nothing
she said in that interview that was
actually coming from her like like a
deep part of her the soul of her it was
all persona it was all persona and and
and all use of words in a in a expedient
manner as tools to obtain I think
probably probably status dominant status
and reputation yeah I mean what advice
would you give to people to to navigate
this new world
the first is free your mind be aware of
the fact that the habits of the blue
church and and how it works don't work
anymore recognize that your way of
making sense in the world that used to
work don't work and you really really
need to set yourself free to begin
learning anew child's mind beginner's
mind second this by nature must in fact
the exploratory so swim do not make
sense prematurely in spite of the fact
that the world feels dangerous inside of
that you may want to
protect yourself in this dangerous world
doing so too quickly does not allow the
natural exploratory approach to do what
it needs to do really just listen and
learn go all the way dad back down to
human base turn it inward learn how fear
shows up in you learn how not to allow
fear to drive the choices that you make
learn how to listen to the whole way
that all of you perceives what's going
on become more integrated with your own
body go out into nature spend a lot of
time not connected to the chaos that's
going on and a lot of time reconnecting
yourself with your fundamental capacity
to perceive reality in all the different
modalities these human beings have the
capacity to do then relearn how to use
other human beings as allies in figuring
out how to make sense of the world I
mean that really relearned like we have
been abused and constrained by
institutional frameworks that remove us
from our own native capabilities so
relearn that understand how to be a
friend and an ally how to have a
conversation with somebody where you're
really listening closely to get a sense
of what their perspective brings to you
well you're not obligated to agree with
them you're not obligated to move out of
what you feel is right to form some new
consensus reality but where you're
actually authentically recognizing that
their perspective has some capacity to
bring richness to your perspective this
by the way is almost exclusively
possible in person and what we're doing
right now is an OK version of it but we
need be very mindful the fact that
linear broadcast is bad and even
interactive bandwidth like this it's not
good enough you know you've got to learn
from raw physical and get yourself into
places where your consensus reality and
your habits are willfully destroyed
human to human conversations and and get
as far away from ideology as you can
your job is not to know what the fuck is
going on your job is to be absolutely
certain that you have no idea what the
fuck is going on and learn how to feel
from raw chaos from raw uncertainty up
then and only then are you finally able
to begin the journey of beginning to
form a collective intelligence in this
new environment that's my advice this is
why we've created rebel wisdom to host
these conversations to try and unpack
what's going on and through our
workshops and events start to build this
collective intelligence for the future
to see longer versions of the interviews
featured in this film and our
full-length documentary about Jordan
Peterson checked the rebel wisdom
website helped us create more films
about the subject by sponsoring us on
patreon and come to our events to have
these conversations in person
[Music]
you